Good morning, very good afternoon, depending on where you are today, for me it is an honor and a
pleasure to interview Nonie Reano, a psychologist, coach, therapist, apart from being a senior consultant
for companies and corporate universities, and belonging to the Brahma Kumaris team. Today
we will talk with her about a topic that touches many of us, anxiety. Thank you Erika, I wanted to
be here with you very happy for the presentation and with all the people who are listening to us
. I love the proposal of this channel to work from a holistic perspective. I am a psychologist and a coach
, so I am going to be able to share an experience as well, however. I have a very, very strong orientation
in the area of ​​Rāja yoga meditation, which is a practice that I have been doing for about 19 years,
so we start with the first question that causes you anxiety that you cannot say because
we live in a chaotic world in a society that It goes to thousand that we do not stop that we are always
that we want to do everything today so you can tell us what causes us especially in
recent years there is a lot of talk about anxiety that's right Erika is a super important topic in reality
sometimes we hear anxiety and we say there is NO, it already gives us anxiety when hearing the word anxiety
is usually generated as in our mind a lot of thoughts of worry is said to
be triggered adena in most cases due to its stress that accumulate over
time when it is a more generalized one, however anxiety is a normal emotion it is
a human emotion as well as joy as well as fear as well as Feeling proud Currently
, there is a huge range of emotions that are already endorsed, let's say not before, only
a few were mentioned that were specific to the main ones, but now we talk about a lot and
anxiety is precisely part of that, it is also an emotion that arises as a mechanism natural response
to defend ourselves with situations in life when I have to take an exam,
attend an interview when I don't know I am in a learning process I have to
pass some type of particular test or health issues so it is normal to experience anxiety
not a little sweating your heart beats your lips dry a little but when this
is already taken to extreme places in our lives and and We have to pay much more attention to
it because at the beginning, as you said, when is this when I have to take an exam or present myself
for an interview, up to a certain point, anxiety, let's say as you said, is normal, of
course, it is normal, it helps is a way that your body responds strangely it would be not to experience
it rather it is not a human emotion it is natural no however when this begins to affect your
life because it begins to be excessive and you feel that you cannot control it there we are already talking
about a disorder let's say what is the differentiation with an emotion as such this is
a disorder and there are many more indicators that speak of a need for treatment or
a search for advice or greater containment let's say and what would be the alert points to
find the limit of anxiety let's say in quotes normal anxiety up to a certain
point where one begins to worry and say I don't have to see a specialist that one
begins to t Let's say anxiety is more common in our daily lives and that's when
we start to feel like it's constant, not that any little thing can trigger it or we don't
even know why it triggered it and we are already experiencing fear or sometimes terror or sometimes like
this anxiety that it makes me not be able to move as I moved on a daily basis in my life or that I
begin to avoid things that were normal before because it generates anxiety there are
alert calls when I suddenly have difficulties in sleeping much more palpitations is when
I begin to see my mind that it is in such a recurring state of connection with worry and that
is very interesting to note because when we experience the emotion of fear, the
emotion of fear activates as a stimulus, thus this response that goes between fight or flight I do not leave or I
fight so internally when these spaces occur you feel like this can't
stop and I have a feeling that I may be losing consciousness I think something is missing or I am
lacking money I am going to lack well-being you lack this I feel that I lack and that sensation
of feeling that I do not have control then it generates such an imbalance in me that I entered a state
of constant disturbance and in a rumination of my thoughts that do not stop and in the emotion of fear
and of course we associate it with anxiety is one of the emotions that most generate thoughts of
ruminating because because you experienced the feeling of being vulnerable in terms of health or in
terms of something physical or material then there all those series of internal sensations begin to activate that of
course cause me discomfort and that my environment also perceives as
different from my usual behavior let's say it's an excessive concern for the future let's
say when being too much in the future and forgetting from the present no this is also
an alert that there is one that has to be attentive not that there is already a signal let's say if
it is so it is like a constant p because one may have had experiences in the past of some kind of
anxiety and suddenly today I begin to visualize in my mind that I could lose that sense again
his look at the future as practically full of uncertainty and my whole
body begins physiologically responses but also This whole chain does not begin to activate mentally
with this intense current of emotion that is not very pleasant of course and clouds me
and then indeed the records of the past begin to activate, my present becomes cloudy
and the future is completely uncertain the other question would be a difference between anxiety
and depressive anxiety? if there is any difference because I don't know what you can tell us
from your point of view if there are several types of anxiety in Erika and one of you is good at
manifesting this anxiety that also carries elements of depression depression-oriented
symptomatology It has to do with sadness, low mood, sleep disturbances
, and appetite difficulties. So, of course, there is a combination of both and, on the other
hand, a state of constant anxiety, although the other question would be how meditation can
help us. end or be in this constant struggle with anxiety how can we start someone who
has never done meditation what can we tell you I am speaking from my own experience because
I have suffered from anxiety so I have come to this in this process of incorporating the meditation that
I do every day and I feel good it has helped me because having the right people and
tools around me that have helped me and continue to help me in this process, and
you, who can tell us how meditation can help us, yes, how wonderful, Erika, the truth is that
meditation can help, how to prevent symptoms or manifestations from becoming more acute,
to help reduce anxiety levels, of course, because when we We talked about there are
a lot of types of meditation, the one I practice is Rāja yoga meditation, which
I am going to tell you a little about because it is what I have closest to me and also as a daily study, what
meditation generates in this case Rāja yoga is that you can generate a space of great silence and
peace for yourself now but if I am anxious how to think about generating a space of calm silence
if the last thing I feel I have, well that is what we generate is a kind of dialogue
with yourself with that side that is profoundly healthy is that sacred space of you that which can also
be known in psychology the elevated SELF what we do is generate spaces to enter
into this connection as SELF and raised as your most genuine non-genuine being as we are going to the one I want I
enter my non-genuine rebellion as the being of peace from being of light into being conscious energy
that you are that can be beyond the shadows of any type of mental imbalance physical hormonal
and in the case of anxiety of course one is aware and can generate this dialogue
with oneself from these parameters then we connect with ourselves as the consciousness
that we are beings of energy that we are beings of peace and we begin to have this encounter with us
in that consciousness when I start talking to myself in that way what I am doing Erika is
silencing all the other types of thought of anguish of worry of accumulated stress
that have been covering my being and my world in some way to be able to activate this other then is
like silencing all this noise to somehow learn the sound of silence but it is not a
silence of anguish on the contrary it is a silence io is like you when you leave and those who are with us today
you who are listening to us go to a place of nature that you love think of that place that
you love in that field in that mountain in that river in that lake in that sea in that clear sky in
those little birds in any natural setting you go at that moment visualize it and suddenly you feel
a state of calm how delicious how pleasant there what you have done is redirect your thoughts
from the catastrophic or negative ones towards more positive and purer ones and the meditation is
precisely that, it is constantly and consciously it is bringing those kinds of thoughts that suit me
quality of life will simply be very powerful that my mind begins to do who
is in control because I am going to begin to take charge of myself and I am going to say look
mind you are going this way because I have the rudder and then the mind that many
times feels owner of me is going to start being educated trained then meditation is a process really
very natural that allows us, of course, to generate a concentration process that helps all
my well-being emerge when we are anxious we cannot concentrate we cannot activate
our cognitive functions very quickly, that is, our thoughts meditation helps you
with that and it is a training that occurs constantly the benefits are incredible they are
wonderful and of course in the reduction of anxiety now if someone is in a treatment
they need to do a treatment of course they have to do it but speaking of anxiety
as a human let's say in the extended meditation is normal, look, it is wonderful if we need a
type of treatment we can also use meditation as an accompanying process, but
it is always good and advisable to use some type of therapy or additional treatment, of course,
if it is already a diagnosis, it is not clear, yes, because it can be used Let's say how I always use
traditional medicine and not traditional You can't put it together and you can take it with you because
meditation in my case has helped me a lot but as you say it was for me when
the first time I had a panic attack it was difficult to do normal meditation let's say keeping my
eyes closed and there I discovered Tai Chi the movements that was where I discovered but now
I am starting again 20 minutes 25 or 30 minutes of the maximum me before
the cancer was detected I had already reached about 40 minutes a day of meditation that was wow but when
at the end of the radiotherapy it was very complicated for me, then from there discovering the Tia Chi that
helped me a lot because the movement and all that but as you say there are several types that each
person can find what suits them best and use the two most traditional and not traditional if
Erika I would like to make a comment about it I love that you bring the experience
of your personal situation and how the fact of meditating and being able to feel a point no
longer helped you meditation was enough that you had to enter another process of personal work you
find Tai Chi and what is perhaps not very precise and I would love to clarify it now that
this meditation process is what I have to do every day and in I do
n't necessarily have to sit down to do this practice at all times, positively it can be very complicated
to be able to stabilize it at the moment when I am already with the red light as well as an alarm, but as
long as I do it as a constant practice like you are not counting every day whenever I
can while I'm moving from one place to another because the meditation that we do is a
meditation that is the movement of these with your eyes open you are in that powerful dialogue
with yourself positive it's like when I hit you song no what are you going to do with it super sticky and
you are in the world in your life you are with the song there then in the same way this exercise of
going again each time that we can so that when the situation arises we can be
much more prepared so that the impact of it can be less, of course, and we can
effectively keep ourselves more stable taichi is a wonderful practice that while doing Tia Chi you
can also do meditation and in this exercise in that movement and you are in connection with your
own being yes yes it is totally true because sometimes it is because I was used to doing
a type of meditation but later with my health problem it cost me for example up to four months
ago because it caused me the attack of I panicked when they started to put me in after
two weeks I had been doing radiotherapy I don't know if you are aware where they put you in
a closed room that the doctors the fact that I was alone I was short of breath then I had and
my problem was being in closed places so there where also when I take a shower or
go up the elevator it doesn't come to me thank god but I always say thank you gr Thank you thank you thank you thank
you but it comes naturally to me because I have been doing it constantly for the last few months that
I am already in a closed place it is not because something comes to me but because it already comes naturally
to me how wonderful my body has got used to it you have not integrated it or what wonderful you know
that while you are telling me this I remember that there are some studies of quantum physics Masaru
Emoto studied water and he realized how it is that there were words that generated a very
strong impact on our minds and on the modifications also of our organism and if the body is
made up mostly of water, then he identified that one of the words that
generated the most positive impact on the mind and that was also reflected in matter was the word
thank you in which you are repeating now, which is like a mantra that helps the mind focus
on something because when we are like you, for example, you share an anxiety attack of an anxiety attack
if it is important now to panic to focus your gaze on something and feel that you are in
your present and bring your present yes then as you do you are seeing that you are exposing yourself to a
place that before suddenly to throw an elevator normally but you get on and see that it you can
drive and you are with this mantra it is like bringing awareness to your present I help you a lot and
meditation favors that we are aware of our present that we do not go to the past
that we are not in the anguish of our future build a good present and what is to come is going to
be wonderful because it is the fruit of today if it is not totally true I think that as you have
said meditation helps us a lot to live in the present which is the most important thing that
sometimes we forget we are worried about what it's over and what's there thinking thinking about the
past is over and the future is uncertain we waste time instead of enjoying a coffee with a friend
or our daily life writing I don't know why what one makes fully present and it is if it
is more important it is what we deserve and live in the present and it is what we have forgotten and
that is precisely why anxiety or anxiety disorders are also generated it is like the
feeling that I am going to be missing I have concerns such as total forgetfulness of the
present tense I totally agree then our next question would be what type
of meditation for a person who suffers from anxiety who cannot say specifically
an appropriate type that you can tell us for a person who suffers from anxiety there are different
types of meditation different wonderful current schools the truth is that all types of meditation
that the person can do will be in fact going to help there are some that are very
oriented to breathing such as mindfulness for example that makes the person connect
with I like the body with the present Raja yoga meditation because it has these two aspects
, maybe at the beginning you can be focusing on breathing ion that is not typical of the practice
but meditation teachers and professors implement it many times because when some
people are going to start meditating sometimes it seems that you are coming from all the accelerated rhythm
then as if you breathe for a while relax do not follow your breath It is like helping
the person to start the process to reset himself, but it is especially the work on the mind
in which Rāja yoga focuses, so that practice that I tell you to remember that we are a
point of conscious energy that is here between the eyebrows at the height behind the eyes
they visualize a star of light there it is very very very powerful and also visualize that there is a
star of light on top that we could call the energy source as each one wants to call it
and the supreme soul or that supreme as we want and take energies as if there were a star
, a sun that is feeding me energy, which is precisely what I do when I am in a state
of fluctuation. n I need I need energy because I feel that I lack and that's why I get sad
it can give me depression, anxiety or all these manifestations of our mind also then
I visualized one as a sun of energies and lighting me lighting it especially in the center of the
forehead and that is the technique that we use of course that if I can do the exercise
do it most of the time better if I can even have an image that helps me
soft music but I am usually more in favor of making our mind work when we put
many external stimuli like a lot of music or a lot of visual image when we are in
daily life having to face challenging situations we are not going to be able to play music
or physically bring an image but if we use the screen of my mind as a projection of the
thoughts that I want to generate then it helps a lot the fact of being able to train your mind and
when I leave knowing let's see that new our mind goes negative quickly as we turn
again you take the wheel and turn and go to a powerful thought a positive thought a
nice statement about yourself and that starts to rewire our
mind-boggling nervous systems and there are parts in the brain that are activated there is not a part of the brain
called the amygdala that quickly responds to fear, then as an alteration in that
sense when there is a very strong emotion sorry when there is a stimulus that generates something in me I
am at a level of greater sensitivity then while I can have all my systems regulated
and quiet better and as I do in prevention in my day to day life I wake up positive thoughts
I have my breakfast where the computer as much as possible positive thinking all the time like
you Erika tell us if it happens a difficult situation of your mind will quickly move towards
where you have trained it is like in the gym the same but internally the internal muscles have
to be trained yes yes yes and what other techniques can we use to combat anxiety and I think maybe
even right now look at using the word fight I think maybe we can modify
our language and not think about how to fight but how go through it because if we can
feel that it is a threat we are going to experience more anxiety then it is already happening if I am
nervous I am anxious that this is normal it is part of the situation in which I find myself at that
moment and I focus on where I want to focus is how am I going to generate positive thoughts about
what right now generates a lot of negative thoughts or am I going to start doing
conscious breathing exercises also always try to make my inhalation shorter than my exhalation
so I inhale, hold for a little while and then exhale towards another installation long and try to make
the breathing diaphragmatic because if it does not stay here, it is not at this level, I repeat small and short and
fast, then the anxiety is triggered, but if I am going to do a breathing exercise a little longer,
be a little more aware of my breathing, there really is a lot of me, the
people who attend consultations, these breathing techniques are really basic, then
there is one that is how to play with the nostrils that is the type of Hindu breathing therapy
how they meet later also when doing physical yoga it helps a lot there are many types of
yoga too but also stretching the physical body helps to go out every day and you can walk resume your
hobbies the things you like is how to generate life or live the life you dream of and that idea that
you dream you generate here, that is, it can be enjoying the simplest things in the world how to go for a walk and
be aware that you are walking you present of your steps bring to your memories beautiful scenes of
your life or bring your goals what you dream about how you visualize yourself all these exercises heal and observe
your talents their capabilities their strengths as they are much more attracted to that and that is why it
is also good to start looking for people who have that same energy who can live the same way to stay away from
conversations that are toxic from information that is toxic that drains you of energy that makes you be
with defensive fear with anxiety is to begin to observe the world and it is really the
process of transformation serious you told me that you had made a change in your life
lately and it seems incredible to me if I this was something very funny because I the dream is always
there because I'm going to live in China for a while in Asian countries but this state
behind I just finished a master's degree in Belgium and I said I'm preparing myself because I was after
a job to go to China and just before cancer came to me they told
me they gave me the job but I couldn't start I was never here for a year with treatment
from no company waiting for you for a year then but it was something miracle and one says oh no because I will go but
and maybe as a motivational coach I already visualize myself I already visualize myself and I go there and
I see myself I am already doing my internships no but things happen for a reason so I have decided
change everything I have decided to serve this is my way that I have found to serve opening using
social platforms telling my experience telling what has helped me interviewing
professional people like you who can help other people because sometimes people are
afraid of talk and then that's what I'm doing transforming my life and everything else.
how exercise helps us good nutrition how all this helps us
together with anxiety meditation good nutrition being always in contact with
nature because in my case it has helped me and continues to help me a lot that we can you say
about it Nonie asu what a good question how beautiful and how nice what you have said that really helps you a
lot the connection with nature is medicine because if we are not in connection with
nature it is most likely that we are involved in it world of telephones in these worlds as
parallels and we stop breathing well we stop moving in a sedentary lifestyle it is fatal fatal
for health in all mental and physical terms so the practice of
physical exercise is wonderful it helps a lot even research has been done where it is said well
that in terms of depression if you walk 20 minutes every day you begin to lift
your mood in such a way that you can even removing some symptoms of the disorder
is wonderful, so it is important to do physical exercise, I told you about yoga
, which is also good, everything that makes my body can also be for small moments
in that self-awareness is like the body has also recorded in its memories is
in situations that have not been so favorable to being in nature I know that in some way
new recordings begin to be generated and that is what we have to point out that is why I emphasized
breathing so much in these exercises that help me to be able to feel connected with the whole the
fact of food is also wonderful because we for example in terms of the
knowledge we have of Rāja yoga of our suggestions is to eat a non-violent or
vegetarian or vegan food and what does this mean when we eat meat what we are doing is
going exactly the opposite and here of course it is a decision each one can make if
they want ere and if nothing happens, it doesn't hurt to hear information that is different from what you
think, not in any case, it is the act of eating meat, it is in some way promoting a violent act, not the
slaughter of an animal, of that animal, in fact it is a living being and it has a more developed nervous system
than a plant and it is generating anxiety fear anguish at the moment of being
slaughtered those emotions are impregnated in the meat that you later eat and that generates an
impact on your mind so first the fact moving away to a peaceful conscience is what
I want to feel when you eat anxiety because I am connecting with a violent act and the other thing
is to take the energy of those animals and unconsciously make it my own that generates a lot
of weight in the mind there has been research we have identified that people who eat meat have
higher levels of aggressiveness than people who do not eat meat and say meat of all
kinds animals not cows fish then it is also a consideration important eration a diet much more
accentuated in vegetables in fibers a measure that your body allows it or it is good for you
or because it makes you good to review it is super super super recommended to lower the sugar lower the coffee
because there are also depressants by For example, alcohol is like a holistic change,
effectively like your channel, like your proposal, Erika, and it's not a small thing, it really is not a small
thing, we are super connected with our minds and our bodies, so if we make a change in
some of these in those dimensions, physical and spiritually the effects are going to be wonderful
at the level of my emotions also not if it is true because for example after my operation I
have been vegan for some time but with my operation it has affected the lower part
of the intestine so some raw vegetables I can't eat them because I get swollen so right
now I'm using the Aryuveda diet where I've found that it's helping me
I'm already with the same diet for three months because i was in peru it worked great for me i got here it
's hot they didn't have to change it with the weather and know the dotcha now and all that very
interesting that is interesting because my body my digestion so i write
everything It hurts me because I want to eat so much, for example, green juices in the morning, right now,
for example, the green juices that I love so much, I can't, for example, and I only make carrots on their own
, it's super cool, but if I put other types of combinations, it won't because I get swollen so but
ready but in my case right now I use Ayurveda but I've been eating healthy for a long
time because ten years ago I had for example that's where I start eating healthy because I got
hormonal acne almost 30 years later I got hormonal acne it was because of the level of stress and leading
a life that was not, let's say, the best when one is young sometimes they don't look well they eat badly they eat
badly and that's where I started obviously that em I sinned little by little people have to start little
by little it's not that from one day to the next one gets up and says I'm vegan I don't eat more meat it's impossible
people have to start little by little for example if they ate
a kilo of meat a week to eat you I don't get half a quarter and so
little by little also incorporating a little more vegetables and fruit
the advice what advice can you leave us to the community the advice you have already given us a lot
of advice during the interview but the complex hospital what a beautiful erika well first before
advice congratulate you for your energy because you look radiant because you know what
is really going on with challenging moments but with an incredible attitude and like all this
that you have done that can be very instructive for him world in general let's say it's like
a way out not that you have found for your recovery and how wonderful that you can
share it with all the people like all of us so congratulations and
what a I could advise that you know that while I was listening I thought that the people who you
who are listening can rest can eat well eat healthy you can read things that
feed the soul find spaces for you so that you can recover your energy meditation
is wonderful there is a lot a lot of a lot of a lot of research about the effects of
meditation in many terms and fields of life the mind really is a wonderful tool
that you connect with what you like I would invite people to connect with life and
feel worthy of it vivir la vida que yo quiero y no estoy hablando de una vida llena
de cosas físicas o materiales porque ir en busca de la felicidad a través de eso es una ilusión en
el amor sino encontrar el amor propio y todas esas hábitos o prácticas que te pueden ayudar
a sentirte amada por ti misma o por ti mismo creo que es como darles y como en el clavo yo
te sugeriría porque es verdad porque uno a veces éste está siempre busc ando todo fuera no pero
todo es parte de acadé el amor hacia nosotros y después el amor hacia sí es que en cuenta está a
limón no ya es otra otro rollo pero tuvo parte de nosotros mismos para encontrarnos encontrarlas a
nosotras mismas al vernos a nosotras mismas nos respetamos y valoramos y sobre todo qué
vivir una vida intencional no sólo aceptar lo que nos toca no como dices tú no fijas nuestras
cosas en las cosas materiales y me compré estos zapatos este vestido voy a ser feliz tú tienes
que ser feliz sin esos zapatos o zapatos porque honestamente debo decirlo yo hace 10 años atrás
seguramente lo más superficial y me acuerdo cuando la primera empresa que a mí me decía difícilmente
y más siendo sudamericana en inglaterra no vas a conseguir trabajo es muy complicado
ejercer tu carrera pero yo siempre aunque si no hacía meditación a la época hace diez años
a ellos y así yo puedo porque no entonces y yo lo logre no y cuando la empresa me daba porque
te dan bonos o ciertas cosas yo feli z por los bonos pero yo ahora lo veo diferente porque
estoy en este en este camino de que las cosas materiales van y vienen pero tú tu amor propio
que era como ha dicho estuvo en el consejo que nos ha dejado y gracias gracias no ni por esta
entrevista maravillosa yo éste ya estaba así yo estaba nerviosa porque de verdad este ha
sido un placer conocerte un poquito más y espero pronto en perú y participar de este evento para
y limpiar es seguir limpiando y seguir viviendo un presente que linda dedica muchas gracias está
encantada de estar contigo y muchísimas gracias por la invitación ya todos ya todas quienes están
escuchando nos esperamos bueno que haya podido ser de utilidad si seguramente si Nonie has dado
muchos consejos importantes que nos va a ayudar a mejorar nuestro estilo de vida sobre todo gracias
Gracias a todos ustedes por haber estado con nosotros espero que esta entrevista
les ayude porque Nonie Reano nuestra psicóloga terapeuta y coach nos ha dejado muchos consejos
muy im portantes si te gustan este tipo de entrevistas por favor ponme un me gusta
deja un comentario comparte la entrevista con personas que le puedan ayudar y no te olvides
de seguirnos en nuestro canal YouTube y nos encontraras en instagram en facebook